<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Dylan Rose</title>
 <link href="http://hamcastle1.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://hamcastle1.github.io/"/>
 <updated>2015-11-16T14:08:19-05:00</updated>
 <id>http://hamcastle1.github.io</id>
 <author>
   <name></name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Schachner, Brady, Pepperberg & Hauser, 2009</title>
   <link href="http://hamcastle1.github.io/2015/11/16/Schachner,%20Brady,%20Pepperberg%20&%20Hauser,%202009/"/>
   <updated>2015-11-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://hamcastle1.github.io/2015/11/16/Schachner, Brady, Pepperberg & Hauser, 2009</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;—————————————&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt;
This post is the beginning of a series that I hope will run as long as the course of my training.
I’ve heard it said that reading a paper a day is good practice for a scientist, and this seems like a fine way to hold my hand to the fire on that score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside eye movement related material (and, realistically, even there), I will almost never have expertise on the subject of anything I read, so gross errors/misinterprations of the paper’s content should get chalked up to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a learning exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objective is for me to read a paper each day and provide both a short summary of its content, as well as a brief summary of my thoughts on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and papers that need to get read for classes/journal clubs count :P .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;—————————————&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today’s Paper:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I read “Spontaneous Motor Entrainment to Music in Multiple Vocal Mimicking Species” by Adrena Schachner, Timothy F. Brady, Irene M. Pepperberg and Marc D. Hauser. This paper was published on May 26, 2009 in Volume 19, Issue 10 of &lt;em&gt;Current Biology&lt;/em&gt;.
It is available, free of charge, at this &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0960982209009154&quot;&gt;link.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s paper concerns the hypothesis that auditory-motor entrainment – roughly, the ability to match motor movements to a beat – is contingent on the capacity for auditory mimicry. The human capacity for entrainment is believed by some to be a marker of human linguistic “uniqueness”.
This is because only a relatively small number of non-human species are thought capable of vocal mimicry, including several types of birds (mostly parrots and songbirds), elephants, cetaceans (dolphins and whales), and some bats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors report that little, if any, systematic evidence attempting to document entrainment in non-human animals has been collected.
Their primary hypothesis is that if the capacity for entrainment is contingent on being able to mimic, then only these species should show evidence of entrainment.
This was tested here by first demonstrating that two bird subjects – a cocatoo and an african grey parrot – could adequately match the phase and rythmn of unknown audio stimuli.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second experiment, a large database of animal videos was analyzed for evidence of equivalent behavior in additional species. Those classified as “vocal mimics” showed significantly more evidence of entrainment than those not so classified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was asked to read this paper for a psycholinguistics pro-seminar. Admittedly, this is way outside my area of experise/interest, but it was a fun and funky (also quick) read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ability to match/mimic sensory patterns seems like an important part of the human linguistic apparatus.
The small amount of evidence I’ve been directly exposed to suggesting linkages between the motor components of the speech-production system and the auditory system make it seem as though the ability to copy a motor plan for speech – both heard and spoken – is an important part of the operation of the langauge system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is especially compelling given evidence of the domain specificity of this relationship – the perception of “visual beats” (whatever those are) apparently does not lead smoothly to entrainment in non-human animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core concept behind this class seems to be a review of the standing argument between those who suggest that language is an innate, specialized faculty of the human brain (“generativists”, think Chomsky &amp;amp; friends) and those who think it is just a product of the brain’s core capacity for extracting and make predictions about statistically regular clusters of sensory data (“connectivists”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As to how this paper relates to this core idea: it certainly is interesting that most of the observed mimicking species (also those that show entrainment) are those that rely crucially on auditory communication for (mostly) social relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may suggest that there is something special about the way that the way evolution, through the brain, has responded to a specialized role for auditory communication by selectively facilitating the ability to map auditory input onto motor-behavior in species where this communication mode is most critical.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
